Finding Aid for the Collection of Turkish Manuscripts LSC.0896
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Title (Romanized): Zeyl-i siyer-i nebevi Uniform title: Zeyl-i Nâbi Title (English): Continuation of the prophetic biographies Alternative titles: ??? ??? ????, Date: 1747 April; Manuscript number: 136; 289 leaves: paper; 213 x 119 mm. bound to 213 x 119 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Burgundy leather with gilt borders around the edges. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b and 257b illuminated. (Box 41)
  This is Nabi's continuation of an earlier biography of the prophet Mu?ammad entitled Dürretü't-taç and written by Veysî (1561-1628). The manuscript also contains the continuation of this continuation by Nazmizade.
- Title (Romanized): Garib-nâme Title (English): Book of strange [things] Alternative titles: ???? ????, Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 137; 205 leaves: paper; 207 x 142 mm. bound to 205 x 144 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with yellow paste-downs; insect and water damage. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; leaves missing from beginning and end. (Box 42)
- Title (Romanized): [Serh-i Mesnevi] Title (English): [Commentary on the Mathnawi of Rumi], Date: 1627 November; Manuscript number: 138; 227 leaves: paper; 200 x 143 mm. bound to 203 x 156 mm.; Layout: 24 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather and paper, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; marginalia; leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 42)
  A Turkish commentary of the mystical poem of Rumi (13th century) written in Persian. A random search of twenty verses in this volume showed no correspondence with the index of verses in Nicholson's edition of the original Mathnawi. Furthermore, the given date of this present commentary's composition (1626, during the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Murat IV [1623-1640]) corresponds with an important clue in Kâtip Çelebi's Kashf al-?unun where he states that in the year 1626, Seyh Ismail Mevlevi came up with what he claimed to be a seventh volume of the Mathnawi, otherwise unattested, and wrote a commentary upon it. This was hotly contested as a forgery by the majority of Seyh Ismail's contemporaries. It appears that the present manuscript is a copy of this spurious seventh volume.
- Title (Romanized): Bedriye Title (English): Relating to Badr Alternative titles: ?????, Date: [18--]?; Manuscript number: 139; 28 leaves: paper; 286 x 92 mm. bound to 290 x 105 mm.; Layout: 27 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black Morocco with red leather stripe around the edges, and dark marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 42)
  Perhaps the same as Gülaboglu Muhammed Askeri, 17th cent.
  A poem in rhyming couplets on Sufism (derived from Seyh Bedreddin?), explaining repentance, asceticism, bravery, struggle with self, etc. It also contains a genealogical list of authority figures.
- Title (Romanized): Vilâyetnâme Title (English): Book of mystical mastery Alternative titles: ???? ???? ???? ?????, Vilâyetnâme-i Hac? Bektas, Manakip, Date: 1909; Manuscript number: 140; 112 leaves: paper; 235 x 184 mm. bound to 232 x 185 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Riqa. Binding: Black cloth on boards with leather stripe over spine; tearing off. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some water damage. (Box 42)
  A biography/hagiography of the thirteenth century Anatolian Sufi master Hac? Bektas Velî. The present manuscript has some similarities to the oldest vita of the same title (Hac?m Sultan, 14th cent.), but comparisons with Rudolf Tschudi's 1914 Berlin edition of the latter shows many divergences from the present manuscript.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i] Ahlak-i muhsini Title (English): [Translation of] the beneficent ethics, Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 141; 169 leaves: paper; 241 x 165 mm. bound to 240 x 165 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, inlaid, with gilt edges, and fore-edge level. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; enclosed in gilt borders. (Box 42)
  A treatise on personal ethics for kings, original composed by ?usayn Vai? Kashifi for the Timurid Sultan ?usayn Bayqara.
- Title (Romanized): Bizaatü'l-mübtedi Title (English): The capital stock of the novice Alternative titles: ????? ???????, Date: 1848; Manuscript number: 142; 282 leaves: paper; 263 x 165 mm. bound to 264 x 165 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Paper on boards and burgundy leather, with yellow paste-downs, and fore-edge level. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; enclosed in red borders for the first few leaves. (Box 43)
  The author prayes Bursa as his birth place (1b).
  An encyclopedic listing of minerals and other material and their uses, arranged alphabetically.
- Title (Romanized): [Mürselât ve ta'birât-i Nasûhî] Title (English): [Letters and interpretations of Nasûhî], Date: 1879; Manuscript number: 143; 170 leaves: paper; 223 x 134 mm. bound to 223 x 134 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh Binding: Green leather, with gilt decorations, fore-edge flap, and yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 43)
  A collection of the correspondence and Koranic exegesis of a certain Mehmet b. Nasûhî (Hanefi Cüneydi Halveti üsküdari) originally compiled in 1702. The manuscript also contains a short poem by a certain M?srî Efendi, as well as the poems of Nasûhî.
- Title (Romanized): Tercüme-i sevak?b Title (English): Translation of shiny stars Alternative titles: ????? ?????, Date: 1616 February; Manuscript number: 144; 221 leaves: paper; 242 x 140 mm. bound to 242 x 143 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Green paper on boards, with black leather tripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; water damage; 1b illuminated. (Box 43)
  A translation into Turkish of a Persian book called Thawaqib-i Manaqib by Hamadani, itself being a abridgment of Aflaki's biography of Anatolian Sufis (the Mevlevis) entitled Manaqib al-arifin. The present translation was undertaken during the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Murat III (1574-1595).
- Title (Romanized): Maksadu'l-aksa Title (English): Destination of the ends of the earth Alternative titles: ???? ?????, Date: 1840 February; Manuscript number: 145; 154 leaves: paper; 240 x 158 mm. bound to 240 x 157 mm.; Layout: Average 21 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, fore-edge flap, and yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; leaves separated. (Box 43)
  Turkish translation of a Persian original on metaphysics and mysticism by Nasafi (Aziz al-Din ibn Mu?ammad, 13th cent.). The manuscript also contains 10 other items:
- Title (Romanized): Tercüme-i kitap-i menazilü's-sairin Title (English): The translation of the book of the stations of itinerant Alternative titles: ????? ???? ????? ????????, Âb-i Hayat, Date: 1841; Manuscript number: 146; 133 leaves: paper; 242 x 171 mm. bound to 239 x 173 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; some water damage. (Box 43)
  The full name of the author is Seyyid Mehmet b. Seyyid Seyh Hâmid b. Seyyid Ahmet b. Seyyid Yahya Faz?l. Note on front end paper identifies him as K?r?mî Karasüî Seyh Mehmet Fakrî Efendi.
  A translation into Turkish of a treatise for the guidance of Sufis by the 11th century Ansari al-Harawi, using his 14 th century commentator Abd al-Razzaq Kashani as well.
- Title (Romanized): [Metn-i Siracüddin tercümesi] Title (English): [Translation of the text of Siraj al-Din] Alternative titles: Ilm-i feraiz, Date: 1745 May; Manuscript number: 147; 214 leaves: paper; 217 x 145 mm. bound to 218 x 143 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Faded paper on boards and brown leather. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 43)
  A translation of Siraj al-Din Sajawandi's Fara'i? al-Sirajiyah, completed in December of 1685.
- Title (Romanized): Netaicü'l-fünûn ve mahasinü'l-mütûn Title (English): The end-all of arts and the cream of texts Alternative titles: ????? ?????? ? ????? ??????, Date: 1772 June; Manuscript number: 148; 103 leaves: paper; 222 x 152 mm. bound to 220 x 150 mm.; Layout: 18 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Burgundy leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap, and yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; illustrations; some water damage. (Box 43)
  A treatise on a variety of arts and sciences (medicine, interpretation of dreams, exegesis, history, jurisprudence, etc.), collected and translated by the author from diverse sources and dedicated to the Ottoman Sultan Murat III (1574-1595).
- Title (Romanized): Nehcü's-sülûk fi siyaseti'l-mülûk Title (English): The highway of itinerants for the politics of kings Alternative titles: ??? ?????? ?? ??????? ??????, Kitap nehc üs-sülûk fî siyaset ül-mülûk, Date: 1798; Manuscript number: 149; 112 leaves: paper; 224 x 142 mm. bound to 221 x 143 mm.; Layout: 27 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Burgundy leather, with gilt decoration, yellow paste-downs, and torn fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 44)
  A manual of ruler-ship for kings, illustrated by tales from early Islamic history. Translated for the Ottoman Sultan Abdülhamit I (1774-1789) from an Arabic original by Abd al- Ra?man Shayzari (12th cent), entitled Nahj al-suluk fi siyasat al- muluk.
- Title (Romanized): [Serh-i divan-i Hâf?z] Title (English): [Commentary on the poetic anthology of ?afi?], Date: [Late 18--]; Manuscript number: 150; 261 leaves: paper; 215 x 159 mm. bound to 213 x 162 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Riqa. Binding: Soft brown leather, with brown leather strap over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; leaves missing from the end. (Box 44)
  Sudi's commentary on the Persian poetry of ?afi? (14th century).
- Title (Romanized): Râna Title (English): The graceful Alternative titles: ????, Date: 1799 April; Manuscript number: 151; 65 leaves: paper; 224 x 136 mm. bound to 223 x 140 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Blue marble on boards and brown leather, with orange paste-downs, and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; illustration on 1b. (Box 44)
  The author refers to himself merely as Refî.
  Long allegorical Sufi poem in rhyming couplets on the soul (personified).
- Title (Romanized): Tercüme-i Milel ve nihal Title (English): Translations of nations and faiths Alternative titles: ????? ??? ? ???, Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 152; 145 leaves: paper; 205 x 125 mm. bound to 205 x 123 mm.; Layout: 23 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded green on boards and brown leather, with yellow paste-downs; insect damage. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; illumination on 1b. (Box 44)
  A treatise on various Islamic sects, being a translation of an Arabic original entitled al-Milal wa-al-ni?al by 'Abd al-Karim Shahrastani (1086?- 1153).
- Title (Romanized): [Yûsuf ve Züleyhâ] Uniform title: Yusuf ve Züleyha Title (English): [Joseph and Zulaykha] Alternative titles: Hamdu'llah Hamdi'nin Yusuf ve Züleiha mesnevisi, Date: no date; Manuscript number: 153; 299 leaves: paper; 205 x 125 mm. bound to 205 x 123 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather; faded and frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; leaves missing from the end. (Box 44)
  The author refers to himself and to his father Seyh Semseddin (Aksemseddin).
  A long versified story of the prophet Joseph, loosely translated after the Persian version of Jami.
- Title (Romanized): Bedayi'ü's-sükûk Title (English): Precious legal document Alternative titles: ????? ??????, Date: [Late 18--]; Manuscript number: 154; 54 leaves: paper; 230 x 165 mm. bound to 230 x 165 mm.; Layout: 23 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Pink paper on boards. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; marginal commentary in Arabic. (Box 45)
  A collection of legal rulings on issues ranging from ritual ablution to charitable endowments, collected by the author from the papers of his teacher Sanizade Hâc Mustafa who was the senior clerk at the court of Mahmud Pasa.
- Title (Romanized): Hadikatü's-süedâ Uniform title: Hadikatü's-sü'eda Title (English): Garden of the blessed folks Alternative titles: ????? ??????, Date: 1807; Manuscript number: 155; 232 leaves: paper; 202 x 147 mm. bound to 200 x 150 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Burgundy leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap, and purple paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; water damage. (Box 45)
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i siyer] Title (English): [The translation of {prophetic} biographies] Alternative titles: Fevâyih'un-nebeviyye fî siyer'il-Mustafaviyye, Date: 1694 June; Manuscript number: 156; 240 leaves: paper; 203 x 126 mm. bound to 201 x 125 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Black leather; gilt-inlaid; front board torn off. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; several quires separated from the beginning; 1b illuminated. (Box 45)
  The author does not refer directly to himself, but to his brother Mehmet Efendi Karaçelebizade.
  A translation into Turkish of the life of the prophet Mu?ammad from a Persian text written by Mu?ammad ibn Masud Kazaruni (d. 1357).
- Title (Romanized): Lemezât-i hulviyye ez leme'ât-i ulviyye Uniform title: [Lemezât: Ag?z tad?: Lemezât-? Hulvî ez- lemâ'at-? ulvî] / Lemezât-? hulviyye ez lemezât-? ulviyye Title (English): Sweet tastes from celestial flashes Alternative titles: ????? ????? ?? ????? ?????, Lemezât, Date: 1744; Manuscript number: 157; 499 leaves: paper; 191 x 131 mm. bound to 190 x 131 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Nakh. Binding: Black leather, inlaid, with orange paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 45)
  Biography of four Caliphs and the Twelve Imams based a wide range of Turkish and Persian histories (12b-13a). Composed during the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Ahmet I (1603- 1617).
- Title (Romanized): Sifa-i ebdan'il-merza fî sirr-i menafi'il-kur'an ve'l- esmai'l-hüsna Title (English): The cure of sickly bodies in the secrets of the benefits of the Koran and the sublime names [of God] Alternative titles: ???? ????? ?????? ?? ?? ????? ?????? ??????? ??????, Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 158; 202 leaves: paper; 225 x 143 mm. bound to 220 x 149 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Green cloth on boards. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; 1b illuminated; marginalia. (Box 45)
  List of prayers and religious chants for curing physical and spiritual ailments.
- Title (Romanized): [The light of Mu?ammad], Date: 1618 November; Manuscript number: 159; 245 leaves: paper; 207 x 145 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Missing. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 45)
  Sufi devotional to the prophet Mu?ammad in verse, interrupted throughout by the phrase "Praise to the light of Mu?ammad".
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i] Minhacü'l-abidin Uniform title: Âbidler yolu Title (English): [Translation of] the Pathway of worshippers, Date: 1644 May; Manuscript number: 160; 327 leaves: paper; 205 x 140 mm. bound to 205 x 143 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, inlaid, with fore-edge flap, and marble paste-downs; badly frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; stained. (Box 46)
  A translation from Arabic to Turkish of Minhaj al-abidin by Ghazzali (1058-1111), laying down regulation and guidance for the believers. According to Kâtip Çelebi's Kashf al-?unun, the translation was undertaken in 1519.
- Title (Romanized): Hikâyet-name Title (English): Story book Alternative titles: ????? ????, Date: [15--]?; Manuscript number: 161; 327 leaves: paper; 260 x 171 mm. bound to 260 x 178 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, with fore-edge flap; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; stained. (Box 46)
  A collection of forty popular tales, written, according the preface, for the edification of the reader.
- Title (Romanized): [Gazavat-i Seyyid Battal] Title (English): [The inspired raids of Seyyid Battal], Date: [16--]; Manuscript number: 162; 311 leaves: paper; 184 x 135 mm. bound to 183 x 134 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Faded green paper over boards, with red leather stripe over spine, and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; water damage. (Box 47)
  A versified version of the legends of the Anatolian folk hero Battal Ghazi, composed during the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Süleyman.
- Title (Romanized): Dürretü't-taç Uniform title: Dürret üt-taç Title (English): Pearl of the crown Alternative titles: ??? ?????, Dürret üt- taç fi sahib-ül miraç, Date: [17--]; Manuscript number: 163; 276 leaves: paper; 185 x 127 mm. bound to 190 x 135 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Purple Morocco, brown leather over spine, gilt, with dark Green marble paste-downs.. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 47)
  Veysî's biography of the prophet Muhammad.
- Title (Romanized): Mecmau'l-mesâili's-ser'iyye fî ulûmi'd-dîniyye Title (English): Compendium of legal questions in religious sciences Alternative titles: ???? ??????? ??????? ?? ?????? ???????, Date: 1595 May; Manuscript number: 164; 168 leaves: paper; 207 x 134 mm. bound to 208 x 140 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Burgundy over boards, with leather stripe over spine, fore-edge flap, and marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 47)
  A collection of legal rulings on a number of problems in religious laws, compiled by the author in 1548.
- Title (Romanized): [Lugat-i Halîmî] Uniform title: Bahrü'l-garaib Title (English): [Halîmî's glossary], Date: 1568; Manuscript number: 165; 263 leaves: paper; 200 x 125 mm. bound to 198 x 124 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Burgundy leather with gilt decoration. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; extensive marginalia; leaves tipped in. (Box 47)
  A glossary of Persian to Turkish, the first volume of the whole work.
- Title (Romanized): [Serefü'l-insan] Title (English): [The nobility of man], Date: [15--]; Manuscript number: 166; 192 leaves: paper; 200 x 125 mm. bound to 199 x 130 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Burgundy leather, inlaid, with pink paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; 1b illuminated; leaves missing between leaves 10 and 11. (Box 47)
- Title (Romanized): Tebyînü'l-meram Title (English): Making the meaning clear Alternative titles: ????? ??????, Date: 1737; Manuscript number: 167; 95 leaves: paper; 216 x 158 mm. bound to 218 x 154 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; marginalia; water damage. (Box 48)
  A commentary on a treatise called Beý ve sera (buying and purchasing) by Hamza Efendi.
- Title (Romanized): Ibret-name Uniform title: Kitab-i ibretnüma, Ibretnüma-y? Lâmiî Efendi, Ibrat namah, Ibretname-yi Lâmiî Çelebi. Title (English): Book of admonition Alternative titles: ???? ????, Date: [15--]; Manuscript number: 168; 146 leaves: paper; 205 x 140 mm. bound to 198 x 137 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Soft brown leather; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 48)
  Written during the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Süleyman the magnificent, it is a compilation of ethical stories in rhyme or prose.
- Title (Romanized): Irsâdü'l-mürid ile'l-murad fî tercemet-i Mirsâdi'l-ibâd Title (English): Guiding the seeker towards what is desired by translating The path of bondsmen Alternative titles: ????? ?????? ??? ?????? ?? ????? ????? ??????, Date: 1635 March; Manuscript number: 169; 242 leaves: paper; 208 x 141 mm. bound to 204 x 138 mm.; Layout: 16 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded paper and brown leather; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; enclosed in red borders. (Box 48)
- Title (Romanized): Vikayetü'r-rivaye fî mesaili'l-hidaye Title (English): The preserving of narratives regarding the issues of guidance Alternative titles: ????? ??????? ?? ????? ???????, Tercüme-i vikaye fi'l-fikh el-serif, Date: 1563 August; Manuscript number: 170; 223 leaves: paper; 210 x 152 mm. bound to 211 x 152 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; leaves separated. (Box 48)
- Title (Romanized): [Enfesü'l-cevahir] Uniform title: [Enfesü'l-cevahir] Title (English): [The most elegant of jewels, Date: 1545; Manuscript number: 171; 142 leaves: paper; 205 x 154 mm. bound to 207 x 166 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with leather stripe over spine, and fore-edge flap; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 49)
  Translation of Koranic commentary, covering chapter 67 (al-Mulk), verse 2 to the end of the Koran. Leaves missing from beginning, but spine title and note on 1a identify the manuscript as the translation of Abu al-Layth al-?amarqandi's Koranic exegesis known as the Ba?r al-ulum.
- Title (Romanized): [Risale-i t?p] Title (English): [Treatise on Medicine], Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 172; 95 leaves: paper; 204 x 146 mm. bound to 203 x 150 mm.; Layout: Average 23 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Soft brown leather, blind-stamped, with leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; marginalia. (Box 49)